Guide to the Graffigny Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Graffigny papers
1730-1758
GEN MSS 353
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13
(76 boxes) +1 portfolio
Collection consists of 59 volumes of correspondence between Mme de Graffigny and François-Antoine Devaux, and one volume of letters from Anne-Catherine Helvétius to Graffigny. Also included are 16 volumes and one portfolio of plays, poems, drafts, notes, legal documents, biographical and genealogical sketches and other papers, generally by or related to Mme de Graffigny.
Grafigny, Mme de (Françoise d'Issembourg d'Happoncourt), 1695-1758
Devaux, François-Antoine, 1712-1796
Helvétius, Anne-Catherine, 1719?-1800
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Phillipps MS 23900. Gift of Hans P. Kraus, 1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The majority of this collection was microfilmed in the early 1970s. However, the film is not of preservation quality, and it cannot be guaranteed to be legible throughout. See the Appendix for a reel-to-volume listing of the film.
FRANCOISE D'ISSEMBOURG D'HAPPONCOURT, MME DE GRAFFIGNY (1695-1758)
Born in Nancy on February 11, 1695, Françoise d'Issembourg d'Happoncourt (or Apponcourt) was the daughter of a prosperous military officer at the court of Duke Leopold of Lorraine. Her father claimed family connections with several German princely families, while her mother was related to the celebrated engraver Jacques Callot. In January 1712, Françoise d'Happoncourt married François Huguet de Graffigny, Chambellan to the Duke of Lorraine. The marriage was unhappy from the beginning and none of the three children it produced survived. The Graffignys separated in 1718; five years later, Mme de Graffigny applied for a formal separation on grounds of the brutal treatments received from her husband. He died under mysterious circumstances in 1725.
An independent woman with a reputation for her wit, Graffigny was soon at the center of the literary, artistic, and scientific circles of the Duchy. It was in that context that she met François-Antoine Devaux, who remained her confidant of choice for the remaining 25 years of her life. In the early 1730s, she fell in love with Léopold Desmarets, son of the composer Henry Desmarets. Their liaison lasted until 1743.
Graffigny's situation at the old court of Lorraine came to an end with the Treaty of Vienna in 1736, which gave the Duchy to the deposed King of Poland Stanislas Leszczynski, father-in-law of Louis XV. In 1738, she left Lunéville and spent two months at Cirey with Voltaire and his friend Mme du Châtelet, whom she had met when they visited Lunéville in 1735. Her well-documented stay ended with a serious rift between Graffigny and her hosts.
In February 1739, Graffigny settled in Paris. Among her new relations was Mlle Quinault, the actress and co-founder of the "Société du bout du banc," which Graffigny was invited to join in 1745. With the assistance of her young cousin Anne-Catherine de Ligniville, she opened her own literary salon. It became one of the most distinguished of its day and was frequented by Rousseau, Turgot, D'Argenson, and Helvétius--who subsequently married Anne-Catherine.
In 1747, the publication of the epistolary novel Lettres d'une Péruvienne made Graffigny famous throughout Europe, a fame confirmed three years later when her play Cénie triumphed at the Comédie-Française. In April 1758, however, La fille d'Aristide was a failure in the same theater. Graffigny died on December 12, 1758.
FRANCOIS-ANTOINE DEVAUX (1712-1796)
François-Antoine Devaux, Mme de Graffigny's principal correspondent, whom she addresses as "Panpan," was born in Lunéville, in the Duchy of Lorraine, on September 16, 1712. His father was a surgeon at the court of Duke Leopold. Devaux graduated from the University of Pont-à-Mousson in 1732. After working as a lawyer in the Nancy Parliament, then as the secretary of his cousin and fellow lawyer Jean-Baptiste Michel, he purchased the office of "receveur particulier des finances" (tax collector) in 1741, a charge he resigned in 1752. Reader to King Stanislas of Poland, he was elected in 1752 to the Société des sciences et belles-lettres of Nancy. A minor poet, Devaux was also the author of a one-act prose comedy, Les engagements indiscrets, which was performed in Paris in 1752 thanks to the protection of Mme de Graffigny. In addition to Graffigny, Devaux's circle of friends included the Marquise de Boufflers and her unhappy suitor the Comte de Tressan, the Prince de Bauffremont, and the Comte de Croix. He remained in Lunéville after the death of Stanislas in 1766, living off a pension the king had granted to him, and died there on April 11, 1796.
Scope and Contents
The Graffigny Papers consist of correspondence, writings and other papers by and about Françoise d'Issembourg d'Happoncourt, Mme de Graffigny, bound into 76 volumes, numbered 1-100, including one portfolio of loose documents. At the death of Mme de Graffigny in 1758, all her personal papers were inherited by her friend and confidant François-Antoine Devaux (1712-1796). When Devaux died, the papers became the property of his friend and heir Mme Durival, who in turn bequeathed them to her heirs, Joseph-Louis-Gabriel Noël and his wife. In the early 1820s, the collection was acquired by Sir Thomas Phillipps, possibly from Count Grigorii Vladimirovich Orloff. It resurfaced in June 1965 when it came up for sale at Sotheby's, London, as part of the first sale of the Bibliotheca Phillippica (Phillipps MS 23900). It was divided into 19 lots (114 to 132). Twelve were acquired by the Bibliothèque nationale, one by Theodore Besterman, and the remaining six by H. P. Kraus, who donated them to Yale in 1968, with the exception of Volumes 6 and 96; these were subsequently acquired by the Pierpont Morgan Library. The volumes not at Yale have been noted in the box-and-folder list as "not in the collection."
Series I, Correspondence (1730-1758), consists primarily of correspondence between Graffigny and Devaux. The letters are bound by correspondent, so that each volume contains letters by one writer. The letters by Graffigny written before 1752 were numbered by Devaux in the order in which he received them. These numbers can generally be found on the back of each letter, with a few on the front or in the margins. Each volume of Graffigny's correspondence contains at least one numbered sequence of about 25 to 50 letters. It appears that some sequences of numbers are repeated in more than one volume. Also included in this series is one volume of letters to Graffigny from her niece, Anne-Catherine de Ligniville d'Autricourt, the future Mme Helvétius. The letters from Mme Graffigny are being published in the multi- volume work Correspondance de Madame de Graffigny by English Showalter et al. (Oxford: Voltaire Foundation, Taylor Institution, 1985-).
Series II, Writings (n.d.), contains plays, poems, drafts, notes, legal documents, biographical and genealogical sketches, and other papers, generally by or related to Mme de Graffigny.
Appendix A: Guide to the Microfilm
Note: For many volumes filmed under Microfilm number 361, the exact reel containing the volume is not known. Where the volume is known to be on one of two reels, the reel column will read "1 or 2" or "3 or 4".
Microfilm number / Reel / Volume / Notes
-----------------------------------------------------------
360 / 1 / 1
360 / 1 / 2
360 / 1 / 3
360 / 1 / 4
360 / 1 / 5
Volumes 6-7 are not in the collection
361 / 3 or 4 / 8
360 / 1-2 / 9
361 / 1 or 2 / 10
361 / 1 or 2 / 11
360 / 2 / 12
Volume 13 is not in the collection
361 / 1 or 2 / 14
361 / 1 or 2 / 15
360 / 2 / 16
360 / 2 / 17
Volume 18 is not in the collection
361 / 1 or 2 / 19
360 / 2 / 20
361 / 1 or 2 / 21
360 / 2 / 22
360 / 2-3 / 23
361 / 1 or 2 / 24
360 / 3 / 25
361 / 1 or 2 / 26
361 / 1 or 2 / 27
361 / 1 or 2 / 28
361 / 1 or 2 / 29
Volume 30 is not in the collection
360 / 3 / 31
361 / 1 or 2 / 32
361 / 1 or 2 / 33
361 / 1 or 2 / 34
360 / 3 / 35
361 / 1 or 2 / 36
362 / 1 / 36
360 / 3 / 37
362 / 1 / 38
360 / 4 / 39
361 / 1 or 2 / 40
360 / 4 / 41
360 / 4 / 42
361 / 1 or 2 / 43
361 / 1 or 2 / 44
360 / 4 / 45
361 / 1 or 2 / 46
360 / 4 / 47
360 / 4 / 48
360 / 4 / 49
361 / 1 or 2 / 50
360 / 5 / 51
361 / 3 or 4 / 52
360 / 5 / 53
360 / 5 / 54
361 / 3 or 4 / 55
360 / 5 / 56
360 / 5 / 57
361 / 3 or 4 / 58
361 / 3 or 4 / 59
361 / 3 or 4 / 60
361 / 3 or 4 / 61
not filmed / 62
361 / 3 or 4 / 63
361 / 3 or 4 / 64
Volume 65 is not in the collection
361 / 3 or 4 / 66
Volumes 67-76 are not in the collection
362 / 1 / 77
362 / 1 / 78
361 / 5 / 79 / Untitled play
361 / 5 / 80
362 / 1 / 81
361 / 5 / 82
361 / 5 / 83
Volumes 84-89 are not in the collection
362 / 1 / 90
361 / 5 / 91
362 / 2 / 92
361 / 5 / 93 / pp. 231-288 only
362 / 2 / 93
362 / 2 / 94
362 / 2 / 95
Volume 96 is not in the collection
362 / 2 / 97
362 / 2 / 98
362 / 2 / 99
362 / 2 / 100
Authors, French -- 18th century -- Archives; Devaux, François-Antoine, 1712-1796; Grafigny, Mme de (Françoise d'Issembourg d'Happoncourt), 1695-1758; Helvétius, Anne-Catherine, 1719?-1800; Phillipps, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1872 -- Ownership
- Correspondence, 1730-59; Series I; 10; (60 boxes)
  - Volume 1. Devaux to Graffigny, 1730-44, n.d. (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Pages 1-146 are undated letters [ca. 1730s] from Paris to Graffigny in Lunéville. Pages 147-394 are letters dated 1738 Sep.-Jan. from Lunéville to Graffigny at Commercy, Demange and Cirey. Pages 395-414 contain a letter dated [Jun.?] 10, 1744
  - Volume 2. Graffigny to Devaux, 1738 (Box 2)
    Includes: no. 1-33. Written from Commercy and Demange
  - Volume 3. Graffigny to Devaux, 1739-42 (Box 3)
    Includes: no. 426-450, 1741-42, interrupted by a quarrel; no. 176-200, 1739, a note says letters 201-302 were burnt; no. 276-300, 1740, many missing. See vols. 10 and 11
  - Volume 4. Devaux to Graffigny, 1739 Jul-Dec (Box 4)
    To Graffigny at various Paris addresses
  - Volume 5. Graffigny to Devaux, 1739-55 (Box 5)
    Includes: no. 126-150, 1739, not in order; no. 400-425, 1741, not in order; no. 701-725, 1744; no. 826-851, 1745, letter on p. 99 is 28 Oct 1755 (unnumbered); no. 951-975, 1746, misnumbered. The pages in each section of vol. 5 are paged individually
  - [Volumes 6 and 7 are not in the collection]
  - Volume 8. Graffigny to Devaux, 1739-40 (Box 6)
    Includes: no. 64-100, 1739, addressed to various friends in Lunéville, but all for Devaux; no. 201-225, 1740
  - Volume 9. Devaux to Graffigny, 1739 Jan-Jul (Box 7)
    Several letters are addressed to "Monsieur Desmarets"
  - Volume 10. Graffigny to Devaux, 1739-55 (Box 8)
    Includes: no. 151-175, 1739, addressed to various friends in Lunéville, but for Devaux; no. 251-275, 1740, many missing; no. 1051-1075, 1746-47, (letter on p. 257 is 6 Sep 1754 (unnumbered), on p. 261 is 25 Oct 1755, [?] 10 Nov 1739, no. 139) ???
  - Volume 11. Graffigny to Devaux, 1739-58 (Box 9)
    Includes: no. 101-125, 1739; no. 226-250, 1740, many missing; no. 601-625, 1743, letter on p. 201 is 18 Oct [1758]
  - Volume 12. Devaux to Graffigny, 1740 Apr-Dec (Box 10)
  - [Volume 13 is not in the collection]
  - Volume 14. Graffigny to Devaux, 1740-43 (Box 11)
    Includes: no. 302-341, 1740; no. 501- 550, 1742-43
  - Volume 15. Graffigny to Devaux, 1744-46 (Box 12)
    Includes: no. 801-825, 1744 [and 1745?], pp. 97-106 (no. 824-825) are bound after p. 318; no. 926- 950, 1745-46; no. 1026-1050, 1746
  - Volume 16. Devaux to Graffigny, 1740-41 (Box 13)
    Some letters in vols. 16 and 17 are addressed to Mlle [Claire-Claude- Louise] Lebrun, Mlle Giro, and Monsieur [Nicolas-François-Xavier] Liébault. These two volumes perhaps split the 1741 letters into two series because of Clairon's [Lebrun's?] trip to Paris, or efforts to evade Mme du Châtelet's spies
  - Volume 17. Devaux to Graffigny, 1741 (Box 14)
  - [Volume 18 is not in the collection]
  - Volume 19. Graffigny to Devaux, 1742 (Box 15)
    Includes: no. 476-500
  - Volume 20. Devaux to Graffigny, 1742 Jan-Dec (Box 16)
  - Volume 21. Graffigny to Devaux, 1742-43 (Box 17)
    Includes: no. 451-475, 1742; letters numbered 561-610, which are in fact no. 550-600, 1743, misnumbered. The error is corrected in vol. 11, where 601-610 are repeated
  - Volume 22. Devaux to Graffigny, 1743 Jan-May (Box 18)
  - Volume 23. Devaux to Graffigny, 1743 Jun-Dec (Box 19)
  - Volume 24. Graffigny to Devaux, 1743-44 (Box 20)
    Includes: no. 626-650. Pp. 51-58 is drafts of a memoir by Devaux on behalf of [Nicolas-François- Xavier] Liébault
  - Volume 25. Devaux to Graffigny, 1744 Jan-Jun (Box 21)
  - Volume 26. Devaux to Graffigny, 1744 Jul-Dec (Box 22)
  - Volume 27. Graffigny to Devaux, 1744-45 (Box 23)
    Includes: no. 650-675, 1744; no. 726-750, 1744; no. 776-800, 1744-45; no. 901-925, 1745
  - Volume 28. Graffigny to Devaux, 1744-48 (Box 24)
    Includes: no. 751-775, 1744; no. 1001-1025, 1746, bound in reverse order; no. 1-50, 1748
  - Volume 29. Graffigny to Devaux, 1744-49 (Box 25)
    Includes: no. 676-700, 1744; no. 201-250, 1749
  - [Volume 30 is not in the collection]
  - Volume 31. Devaux to Graffigny, 1745 Jan-Jun (Box 26)
  - Volume 32. Devaux to Graffigny, 1745 Jul-Dec (Box 27)
  - Volume 33. Graffigny to Devaux, 1745-47 (Box 28)
    Includes: no. 851-876, 1745; no. 876-900, 1745; no. 1076-1100, 1747
  - Volume 34. Anne-Catherine Helvétius to Graffigny, 1745-46 (Box 29)
  - Volume 35. Devaux to Graffigny, 1746 Jan-Jun (Box 30)
  - Volume 36. Graffigny to Devaux, 1746-49 (Box 31)
    Includes: no. 976-1000, 1746; no. 101-150, 1748-49
  - Volume 37. Devaux to Graffigny, 1746 Jul-Dec (Box 32)
  - Volume 38. Devaux to Graffigny, 1747 (Box 33)
  - Volume 39. Devaux to Graffigny, 1747 (Box 34)
  - Volume 40. Graffigny to Devaux, 1747-48 (Box 35)
    Includes: no. 1151-1186, 1747. A note says the rest to 1200 were burnt, but it would appear that the series ends with Devaux's departure for Paris; no. 51-100, 1748
  - Volume 41. Devaux to Graffigny, 1748 (Box 36)
  - Volume 42. Devaux to Graffigny, 1748 (Box 37)
  - Volume 43. Devaux to Graffigny, 1749 (Box 38)
  - Volume 44. Graffigny to Devaux, 1747-49 (Box 39)
    Includes: no. 1101-1150, 1747; no. 151-200, 1749. The two sections in vol. 44 are paged individually
  - Volume 45. Devaux to Graffigny, 1749 (Box 40)
  - Volume 46. Graffigny to Devaux, 1749-50 (Box 41)
    Includes: no. 251-300
  - Volume 47. Devaux to Graffigny, 1750 (Box 42)
  - Volume 48. Devaux to Graffigny, 1750 (Box 43)
  - Volume 49. Devaux to Graffigny, 1750 (Box 44)
  - Volume 50. Graffigny to Devaux, 1750-51 (Box 45)
    Includes: no. 425-450, 1751; no. 301-350, 1750; no. 401-424, 1750
  - Volume 51. Devaux to Graffigny, 1750 (Box 46)
  - Volume 52. Graffigny to Devaux, 1750 (Box 47)
    Includes: no. 351-400
  - Volume 53. Devaux to Graffigny, 1751 (Box 48)
    First two letters appear to be 1742 and 1743, the rest are 1751
  - Volume 54. Devaux to Graffigny, 1751 (Box 49)
  - Volume 55. Graffigny to Devaux, 1751 (Box 50)
    Includes: no. 452-516, no. 515- 516 are incorrectly numbered as 505-506
  - Volume 56. Graffigny to Devaux, 1751 (Box 51)
    Includes: no. 508-550 [some letters are numbered only in pencil]
  - Volume 57. Graffigny to Devaux, 1752 (Box 52)
  - Volume 58. Graffigny to Devaux, 1752 (Box 53)
  - Volume 59. Graffigny to Devaux, 1753 (Box 54)
  - Volume 60. Graffigny to Devaux, 1754 (Box 55)
  - Volume 61. Graffigny to Devaux, 1753 (Box 56)
    Vol. 60, with pages numbered 289-340, appears to be part of this volume
  - Volume 62. Graffigny to Devaux, 1754-55 (Box 57)
  - Volume 63. Graffigny to Devaux, 1741-56 (Box 58)
    Includes: no. 342-369, 1741; pp. 95-110 are unnumbered letters, 1756; no. 370-400, 1741
  - Volume 64. Graffigny to Devaux, 1756-[58?] (Box 59)
  - [Volume 65 is not in the collection]
  - Volume 66. Graffigny to Devaux, 1758-59 (Box 60)
    A number of these letters were dictated
- Writings, n.d.; Series II; 2; (15 boxes) + 1 portfolio
  [Volumes 67-76 are not in the collection]
  - Volume 77. La fille d'Aristide, professional copy (Box 61)
  - Volume 78. Various plays, in various hands (Box 62)
  - Volume 79. Plays (Box 63)
    Includes: One untitled play, professional copy; Le temple de la vertu, "comédie en un acte"; professional copy; Celidor [?]; Les Mécontents, "Comédie en trois actes et en vers," professional copy; Ziman et Zenise, "Comédie en un acte, représentée à Schoenbrun, les 9, 13, 16 Octobre 1749," professional copy; Héraclite, prétendu sage, in various hands[?]; Ziman et Zenise, professional copy
  - Volume 80. Les effets de la prévention, "Comédie en 5 actes," professional copy (Box 64)
  - Volume 81. Plays (Box 65)
    Includes: Les Saturnales, "Comédie en trois actes," professional copy; Les effets de la prévention; Fille Aristide, "Comédie en cinq actes, pour Souffler"; Le temple de la vertu
  - Volume 82. Plays (Box 66)
    Includes: Les tuteurs, "Comédie en un acte en prose"; L'épouse généreuse, "Drame"; Le sentiment récompensé, "Comédie en 3 actes"; Azakia, ou les reconnaissances, "Comédie en 3 actes en prose"
  - Volume 83. Plays (Box 67)
    Includes: Saïs, "Tragédie en musique"; L'école des amies, "Comédie en 5 actes," outline only; Hadis et Hunnon [by Devaux], "Tragédie en 5 actes et en vers"; untitled play, including Italian translation; La réunion du bon sens et de l'esprit; L'ignorant présomptueux, "Comédie en un acte"
  - [Volumes 84-89 are not in the collection]
  - Volume 90. Plays (Box 68)
    Various plays, including La fille d'Aristide, in various hands
  - Volume 91. Plays (Box 69)
    Includes: Les Saturnales, "Comédie en trois actes," professional copy; La fille d'Aristide, "Comédie," professional copy; L'éducation inutile, "Comédie en un acte," professional copy; Le Temple de la vertu, "Comédie en un acte," professional copy; Les deffauts copiez [Les défauts copiés], "Comédie en un acte," professional copy
  - Volume 92. Plays (Box 70)
    Includes: L'art aux humains est nécessaire; unidentified drafts; Théonise ou l'abus de la philosophie; La fille d'Aristide; La réunion de Minerve et de Vénus, "Prologue de la fête donnée à S.A.S. Mde. la Princesse Frédérique de Brandebourg..."
  - Volume 93. Plays and other writings (Box 71)
    Includes: Héraclite, various drafts; Les Saturnales, "Comédie en trois actes"; Theonise ou l'abus de la philosophie, i.e. La fille d'Aristide, "Comédie en cinq actes en prose," outline; "Chanson composée pour les Grenadiers du Régiment du Roy sur l'air Mr. les Allemands (1741); "Prédictions pour l'année mil sept cent quarante six," poem; "Le mariage," poem; several untitled poems, epigrams, songs; more drafts relating to La fille d'Aristide
  - Volume 94. Various writings (Box 72)
    Includes: "Epitre à Madame de Graffigny"; a petition to the King in favor of the Marquis de Tavanes; "Brevet de la calotte à Mr de la Popelinière"; "Epitre burlesque de Piron au Roy de Prusse"; "affiches des pièces qui ont été représentées dans plusieurs cours de l'Europe, pendant le mois d'août 1744"; "L'amour pour l'amour de Congreve" (prose outline); "Harangue à Madame la comtesse de Custine" (1744, printed item); "Chanson sur Mr. le Duc de Richelieu..."; holograph letter, partly in verse, to Devaux (Nancy, 18 Sep 1743); a collection of 19 Latin epigrams; "Jugement rendu en dernier ressort par Momus Conseiller d'Etat d'Appollon Lieutenant General de Police et messieurs les Commissaires en cette partie contre Arrouët dit Voltaire" ("signé Pellegrin Greffier"); "Prolegomena Martini Scribleri ou sentiments du docteur Swift sur la Dunciade ou Busiade..." (beginning is on p. 167, continues on pages 89-96); "Le plan de Sophonisbe tragedie angloise"; "Description de la feste donnée à Versailles, à l'occasion du mariage de Madame Louise-Elizabeth, Fille Aînée du Roy, avec Dom Philippes Infant d'Espagne" (1739, printed item); "Description sommaire de la feste ordonnée par messieurs les prevost des marchands et echevins de la ville de Paris, Et qui sera éxécutée le Samedy 29 Août 1739, pour le Mariage de Madame avec l'Infant Dom Philippe" (1739, printed item); many various songs, theatrical and poetic drafts throughout
  - Volume 95. Writings and papers (Box 73)
    Includes: various lists and memoranda (mostly dated 1746); Le Magazin &c. La Haye. Mardi, 17 Septembre 1743 (printed item); various drafts; "Le faucon et les pigeons"; "Le coq et la poulette"; various poetical drafts; "Chansons faites sur les eaux de Plombieres. Par Messieurs ______" (n.d., printed item)
  - [Volume 96 is not in the collection]
  - Volume 97. La fille d'Aristide (Box 74)
    Three complete drafts with holograph corrections
  - Volume 98. Papers (Box 75)
    "Papiers d'affairs de Md de Graffigny," including notes on Jacques Callot (Graffigny's great-uncle) and various legal documents, some of them signed by Graffigny
  - Volume 99. "Pièces relatives à la famille de Mme de Graffigny. Actes etc."
  - Volume 100. Papers (Box port)
    Includes: Two documents with paper folder: "Mémoire pour servir a la vie de Madame de Graffigny" and a draft of another memorandum
- Oversize, 1; (1 box)
  - Volume 99. "Pièces relatives à la famille de Mme de Graffigny. Actes etc." (Box 76)